Guide to the Center for Documentary Studies records, 1990-ongoing UA.26.03.0016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Center for Documentary Studies records
1990-[ongoing]
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
UA.26.03.0016
14.6 Linear Feet
The Center for Documentary Studies opened in January 1990 and is an outgrowth of and replacement for the Center for Documentary Photography (1980-1990). The Center combines traditions of documentary photography and film, writing, oral history, and scholarly analysis in seeking to capture life experiences. Collection contains publications, calendars, announcement, brochures, newspaper and magazine clippings, a videocassette, and other materials such as administrative files and electronic files. The materials date from 1990 and the collection is ongoing.
13,050 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Provenance
The Center for Documentary Studies records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1990, 1992, 2000, 2010-2011.
Biographical/Historical note
The Center for Documentary Studies opened in January 1990 and is an outgrowth of and replacement for the Center for Documentary Photography (1980-1990). Creation of the CDS was approved by the Board of Trustees in February, 1989. It was a non-profit support corporation for the University, and was initially funded through a $5 million gift from the Lyndhurst Foundation (1988). The Center combines traditions of documentary photography and film, writing, oral history, and scholarly analysis in seeking to capture life experiences, particularly in four areas of research: the American family, African American life and race relations, law and politics, and ecology and the environment. Directors: Iris T. Hill, 1990-1998; Tom Rankin, 1998-.
Scope and Contents note
Collection contains publications, calendars, announcement, brochures, newspaper and magazine clippings, a videocassette, and other materials. Publications include Up for Grabs (1996-). Also included is a videocassette of the opening of the CDS, 23 January 1990, features remarks by Center director Iris Hill, and Dean R. A. White, Robert Coles, and Reynolds Price. Accessions UA2010-0024 and UA2011-0003 contain promotion materials including exhibit postcards and administrative records. The administrative records are restricted for 25 years from date of origin.
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004.
University Archives, Duke University.
Brodie (H. Keith H.), President, Records, 1963-1994.
University Archives, Duke University.
Building Reference Collection, 1972-2004 (see Lyndhurst House).
University Archives, Duke University.
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004 (see Tom Rankin).
University Archives, Duke University.
Documentary Studies. Audio Documentary Institute student projects, 2003 Summer.
Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Larry Schwarm photographs, 2003.
Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Indivisible: Stories of American Community records, 1999-2002.
Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Literacy through Photography records, 1990-2000.
Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
South African photograph collection.
Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Behind the Veil: Documenting African-American Life in the Jim Crow South. 1940-1997 and undated
Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Walker Evans photographs, 1935-1936.
Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
- Container List, 1 boxes
  - Flyers, 1993-2001 (Box 1)
  - News releases, memos (Box 1)
  - Calendars, undated, 1992, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Up for Grabs, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Dedication, Jan. 23, 1990 - 3M Broadcast VHS T-120 Videocassette (remarks by Iris T. Hill, R.A. White, Reynolds Price, Robert Coles) (Box 1)
- UA2010-0024 circa 1996-2010, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  This accession is not processed.
  - Promotion materials on exhibits, including postcards (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 1) (Box 2)
- UA2011-0003 circa 1994-2002, 9 boxes
  This accession is RESTRICTED as it contains administrative files and is unprocessed. The accession included 4 ZIP disks and a 3.5 inch floppy which were separated from the collection. Their contents were migrated to the server. The originals are stored elsewhere. The contents appear to be related to the exhibit on William Gedney. Please consult Research Services staff before coming on-site so that the electronic files can be reviewed.
  - Contents of Box: circa 1995-1998 Restricted (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 1) (Box 3)
    - CDS General (not specific to exhibitions) (Box 3)
    - Opening of Bridges Building (Box 3)
    - Continuing Education (Box 3)
    - Document Publication (Box 3)
    - Up for Grabs Publication (Box 3)
    - Bridges Bulletin Publication (Box 3)
    - Community Projects (Box 3)
    - Outreach (Box 3)
    - Classes (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes (Box 3)
    - Student Fellowships (Box 3)
  - Contents of Box: circa 1994-1998 Restricted (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 2) (Box 4)
    - Materials related to the following exhibitions: 25 and Under; Appeal to this Age: Photography of the Civil Rights Era; Red White and Blue and God Bless You: A portrait of northern New Mexico; Robert Frank: The Americans; House and Home: Spirits of the South/The Collecting Impulse; Margaret Sartor: Home; Eye of Childhood: Children's Drawings Collected by Robert Coles (Box 4)
  - Contents of Box: circa 1998-1999 Restricted (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 3) (Box 5)
    - Material related to the following exhibitions: HIV Positive Life; S.E.E.D.S.; On the Plains; E.K. Powe Neighborhood Project (Box 5)
    - CDS General (not specific to exhibitions) (Box 5)
    - Matt Devries and Jen Schradie film The Golf War (Box 5)
    - Troubled: Photography, Film and Video from Northern Ireland (Box 5)
    - Corridor of Change (Box 5)
    - John Hope Franklin Presentations (Box 5)
    - Porch Gallery Lamba Youth (Box 5)
    - Lange Taylor Prize (Box 5)
  - Contents of Box: circa 2001-2002 Restricted (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 4) (Box 6)
    - Material related to the following exhibitions: Women and the Music of Rural America; Short Distances and Definite Places: The Photographs of William Gedney; Personal Histories; Inside/Outside: An Installation by Tuba Oztekin; Off Center: CDS Photography Group Show (Box 6)
  - Contents of Box: circa 1997-1999 Restricted (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 5) (Box 7)
    - CDS General (not specific to exhibitions (Box 7)
    - Management Description (Box 7)
    - Job Descriptions and Budgets (Box 7)
    - Promotional Material (Box 7)
    - Travel Expenses (Box 7)
    - Budget for Exhibitions (Box 7)
    - John Hope Franklin Award (Box 7)
    - Material related to the following exhibitions: 25 and Under; Vietnam (Box 7)
  - Contents of Box: circa 1996-1998 Restricted (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 6) (Box 8)
    - Material related to the following exhibitions: The New American Ghetto by Camilo Vergara; H.O.P.E.,; Come Sunday by Thomas Roma (Box 8)
  - Contents of Box: circa 1994-1998 Restricted (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 7) (Box 9)
    - Material related to the following exhibitions: Youngest Parents; Literacy through Photography; Ghana: Two Weeks, Nine Students, Many Cameras (Box 9)
    - Traveling Exhibitions (Box 9)
    - Eye of Childhood (Box 9)
    - CDS General (not specific to exhibitions (Box 9)
    - Budgets and Fundraising (Box 9)
  - Contents of Box: circa 1999-2000 Restricted (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 10) (Box 10)
    - Material related to the following exhibitions: Fast Forward: Growing Up in the Shadow of Hollywood by Lauren Greenfield; El Periodo Especial in Cube by Ernesto Bazan; In My Community: Documenting Changing Life in Durham; Cambodia x3: Facing Death, Cambodia Now, Across Temple Gate (Box 10)
    - CDS General (not related to exhibitions) (Box 10)
  - Contents of Box: circa 2000 Restricted (Box label reflects how box was numbered at accessioning, i.e. Box 11) (Box 11)
    - Material related to the following exhibition: To Conserve a Legacy: American Art from historically Black Colleges and Universities - Training the Head, the Hand, and the Heart (Box 11)
    - Porch Gallery Archive (Box 11)
- UA2011.0033circa 1998-2002, 1 box and 4 folders
  This accession contains materials pertaining to CDS traveling exhibitions.
  - Contents of Box: circa 1998-2002 (Box 11)
    - The Youngest Parents [Photographs by Jocelyn Lee and John Moses] (Box 11)
    - A Positive Life [Photographs by Mary Berridge] (Box 11)
    - Short Distances and Definite Places [Photographs of William Gedney (Box 11)
    - Who Am I? A Decade of Literacy Through Photography in Durham 1990-2000 (Box 11)
  - Contents of Box: circa 1990-2011 (Box 23)
    - Takeover: The Trials of Eddie Hatcher, Publicity circa 1998 (Box 23)
    - Helen Levitt: Children's Street Drawings, Publicity circa 1990 (Box 23)
    - Closing: The Life and Death of an American Factory, Bill Bamberger 1998 (Box 23)
    - House and Home: Spirits of the South 1995-1996 (Box 23)
    - The Eye of Childhood: Children's Drawings Collected by Robert Coles 1994 March-May (Box 23)
    - Porch Gallery 1999 January-May (Box 23)
    - Double Take Documentary Film Festival 1999 April (Box 23)
    - Porch Gallery Exhibitions 1999-2000 (Box 23)
    - Publicity Mailing circa 1998-1999 (Box 23)
    - Double Take Documentary Film Festival 1998 April (Box 23)
    - Publicity Mailing 1999 (Box 23)
    - Twenty-five and Under/Photographs 1997 January-March (Box 23)
    - The New American Ghetto 1997 October-December (Box 23)
    - Mexico City 1941, Helen Levitt; Bearing Witness, Gertrude Blom 1998 February-May (Box 23)
    - Porch Gallery Mailer 1998-1999 (Box 23)
    - Literacy Through Photography Program circa 2000 (Box 23)
    - Thirteen-Month Crop circa 2000 (Box 23)
    - Youth Document Durham, Home Made Visible 2002-2004 (Box 23)
    - Putting Documentary Work to Work 2001 (Box 23)
    - CDS Exhibit Collections circa 2009 (Box 23)
    - S.E.E.D.S. Exhibition 1999 June-July (Box 23)
    - E. K. Powe Neighborhoods Project 1999 June-September (Box 23)
    - On the Plains, Photographs by Peter Brown 1999 (Box 23)
    - Old Five Points Photo Project 1998 September-October (Box 23)
    - Robert Frank: The Americans 1995-1996 (Box 23)
    - I-26, Corridors of Change, Rob Amberg and Sam Gray 1998 April (Box 23)
    - Wendy Ewald: Portraits and Dreams circa 1993 (Box 23)
    - Undraborn/Extraordinary Child Photographs, Mary Ellen Mark 2009-2010 (Box 23)
    - The South in Black and White 2011 (Box 23)
  - The South in Black and White Posters (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Event Posters (Oversize-folder 2)